<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
   
    <title>reasoniamhere.com - Tag: writing</title>
   
   <link>http://reasoniamhere.com</link>
   <description>I am a Spanish-born bioinformatics PhD student living in Boston</description>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <managingEditor>Nacho Caballero</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

    
      <item>
        <title>How To Tell A Good Story From A Bunch Of Random Facts</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/08/01/how-to-tell-a-good-story-from-a-bunch-of-random-facts</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2014-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/08/01/how-to-tell-a-good-story-from-a-bunch-of-random-facts</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p class="center">
<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/37623498" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px 1px 0; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe>
</p>

<p>Stories are finished products. They are the end result of a long process to filter out dead ends and to transform awkwardly phrased ideas into clear thoughts. If you&rsquo;ve never enjoyed writing, it might be because <strong>you have unrealistic expectations about what writing should feel like</strong>. Telling a good story is hard because it requires picking the right ideas, assessing their relevance, developing them into finer details and presenting them in the right order.</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<p>Dennis Overbye opens his <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/15/science/15cern.html?pagewanted=all">excellent New York Times article</a> with this paragraph about the ATLAS particle detector at the Large Hadron Collider in Geneva:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Physics, after all, is supposed to be a cerebral pursuit. But this cavern almost measureless to the eye, stuffed as it is with an Eiffel Tower&rsquo;s worth of metal, eight-story wheels of gold fan-shape boxes, thousands of miles of wire and fat ductlike coils, echoes with the shriek of power tools, the whine of pumps and cranes, beeps and clanks from wrenches, hammers, screwdrivers and the occasional falling bolt. It seems no place for the studious.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This paragraph is not a first draft, it&rsquo;s a highly polished description with plenty of stylistic flourishes and powerful visuals. <strong>It did not start out like this</strong>. My bet is that, during his trip to Geneva, Overbye jotted down something like &ldquo;Talk about the size of ATLAS. Also, mention the noise at the construction site.&rdquo; Then, he went back home, took out his notebook, and spent a few hours developing that vague idea into an enticing introduction.</p>

<h2>Make a list of everything that could belong in the story</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/okHLC9Vl.jpg" alt="random facts"></p>

<p>The first step in writing a good story is choosing the building blocks. At the beginning of the writing process you can&rsquo;t predict which ideas will make it to the final story. What you <em>can</em> do is write down everything you feel might be potentially relevant.</p>

<p>This is a list I made up based on Overbye&rsquo;s paragraph:</p>

<ul>
<li>The ATLAS detector is huge</li>
<li>ATLAS was designed to detect interactions between highly massive particles</li>
<li>There are 3000 physicists working on the project</li>
<li>ATLAS can measure a broad range of signals from the Large Hadron Collider</li>
<li>The construction site is busy and loud</li>
</ul>

<p>Once you have a list, you can start improving it and fixing its shortcomings, but not before.</p>

<p>Write, criticize, repeat.</p>

<h2>Organize ideas into common themes</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/uViWz5Ql.jpg" alt="common themes"></p>

<p>When you write down your thoughts in raw form, you give your working memory permission to focus on more useful things, like extracting related ideas from your subconscious, or finding non-obvious connections between different themes.</p>

<p>For example, we can group the ideas from the previous list into categories:</p>

<ul>
<li>The scale of the ATLAS project

<ul>
<li>The ATLAS detector is huge</li>
<li>3000 physicists are working on the project</li>
<li>The construction site is busy and loud</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Why ATLAS was built

<ul>
<li>ATLAS was designed to detect interactions between highly massive particles</li>
<li>ATLAS can measure a broad range of signals from the Large Hadron Collider</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<p>This is more useful when applied to a longer story (like a presentation) rather than a single paragraph, but the approach is the same. Grouping ideas makes it easier to see which ones point to the same direction, which ones are redundant, and which ones are just there for sentimental reasons.</p>

<h2>Develop ideas that grab your interest</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/1C7h2hfl.jpg" alt="grabbing"></p>

<p>Not every idea you write down will appear in the final story. Some ideas are only useful because they provide a vantage point to discover even better ideas. This is crucial: <strong>it&rsquo;s easier to generate good ideas by improving average ones than by waiting for sudden flashes of inspiration</strong>.</p>

<p>In the ATLAS example, the author chose to focus on the size of the detector and on the frenzy of activity at the construction site. One of the biggest problems about the way we communicate scientific research is that we often state ideas without developing them. &ldquo;The detector is huge&rdquo; is not as interesting to someone unfamiliar with the project as &ldquo;The detector is stuffed with an Eiffel Tower&rsquo;s worth of metal&rdquo;. Here is an example outline illustrating each idea:</p>

<ul>
<li>The ATLAS detector is huge

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s eight-stories high</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s made up of tons of metal (more than the Eiffel tower)</li>
<li>It contains multiple gold-plated boxes</li>
<li>It houses a bunch of wires and coils</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The construction site is busy and loud

<ul>
<li>There are workers everywhere</li>
<li>There are lots of noisy power tools (pumps, cranes, wrenches, and hammers)</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<p>In this example, I&rsquo;ve chosen to ignore the bit about the number of physicists and the goals of the project. When you apply this technique to your own stories, feel free to ignore ideas that are hard to develop. If <em>you</em> are not excited about them, your audience will probably feel the same way.</p>

<h2>Create a transition for every new idea</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5AG13hTl.jpg" alt="transitions"></p>

<p>When you&rsquo;re giving a presentation (that is, when you&rsquo;re telling a story), it&rsquo;s tempting to transition between ideas by simply pressing the <em>Next Slide</em> button. This is the biggest reason why people get lost during a talk. If the audience misses the connection between what you were talking about before and what you&rsquo;re talking about now, you need a better transition. When the transition is good, people nod and they feel like they get what you&rsquo;re saying.</p>

<p>For example, what is the connection between <em>physics</em> and <em>the ATLAS construction site</em>? The author could have simply stated the physical principles that shaped the design of the detector, and then listed a bunch of technical information about dimensions, detection ranges and monetary costs. Instead, Overbye came up with a clever way to bridge these two concepts:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Physics, after all, is supposed to be a cerebral pursuit. But this cavern almost measureless to the eye, [description of scale] echoes with the shriek of power tools [description of noise]. It seems no place for the studious.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You probably wouldn&rsquo;t use the expression <em>almost measureless to the eye</em> in an oral presentation or a scientific article but, regardless of the medium where you present your story, the lesson is the same: <strong>joining unrelated ideas is more satisfying than presenting them separately</strong>.</p>

<h2>The story &amp; everything that didn&rsquo;t make it</h2>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Xas5Dk3l.jpg" alt="everything else"></p>

<p>Transforming a bunch of random facts into a compelling story requires time and energy, but it also requires setting the right expectations. We are constantly exposed to the finished products of talented writers, but we rarely get to see the ugly intermediates and the failed attempts that preceded them. Every time you run across a good story or an obvious solution to a difficult problem, remember that you&rsquo;re only seeing a fraction of the work that was involved.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Write Awesome Abstracts</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/06/29/how-to-write-awesome-abstracts</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2014-06-29T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/06/29/how-to-write-awesome-abstracts</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/lBAZuh1l.jpg" alt="Abstract"></p>

<p>Seminar and conference organizers ask speakers to submit abstracts before they give a presentation. They do it because abstracts have the potential to convince people who could benefit from attending your talk to actually show up. Unfortunately, most abstracts are only effective at keeping attendees away.</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<p>Take the first paragraph from this typical abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Target structure-based “hit” optimization in a drug discovery project is challenging from the computational point of view. Scoring functions cannot predict binding affinity, thus, computational chemists must use their intuition or prior knowledge about the target class to prioritize compounds for synthesis.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Would you like to attend this talk?</p>

<p>Potential audience members that read this abstract will fall into one of these three camps:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>indifferent bystanders</strong>, people who are completely uninterested in the subject, even if the presenter was the Nobel prize winner in &ldquo;Target Structure-Based Hit Optimization.&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p><strong>teachable newbies</strong>, people who could potentially enjoy TSBHO if somebody explained it to them properly.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>driven experts</strong>, people who think that TSBHO is truly important and fundamentally interesting.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>How you write your abstract will influence how many people from each group show up.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s analyze the structure of the previous paragraph by breaking it up into sentences and abstracting away the details:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>A</strong> is challenging from the computational point of view. (Target structure-based “hit” optimization in a drug discovery project is challenging from the computational point of view.)</p></li>
<li><p><strong>B</strong> cannot predict <strong>C</strong>. (Scoring functions cannot predict binding affinity.)</p></li>
<li><p>Thus, computational chemists must use <strong>D</strong> to prioritize <strong>E</strong>. (Thus, computational chemists must use their intuition or prior knowledge about the target class to prioritize compounds for synthesis.)</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Looking at the bare-bones structure makes it easier to determine why some sentences work and others don&rsquo;t. The problem with this paragraph is that it contains technical terms that lack context (A, B, C and E). Driven experts might be able to fill in the gaps, but teachable newbies will either miss the point or stop reading (if they attend the talk, it will be for the free pizza).</p>

<p>Compare the previous example with this one:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The chemotaxis network of bacteria such as E. coli is remarkable for its sensitivity to minute relative changes in chemical concentrations in the environment. Indeed, E. coli cells can detect concentration changes corresponding to only ~3 molecules in the volume of a cell. Much of this acute sensitivity can be traced to the collective behavior of teams of chemoreceptors on the cell surface.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Would you attend this talk?</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t know much about chemotaxis before I read it, but it got me interested.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s do the same split-and-simplify breakdown:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>A</strong> is remarkable for its sensitivity to <strong>B</strong>. (The chemotaxis network of bacteria such as E. coli is remarkable for its sensitivity to minute relative changes in chemical concentrations in the environment.)</p></li>
<li><p>Indeed, E. coli cells can detect <strong>C</strong>. (Indeed, E. coli cells can detect concentration changes corresponding to only ~3 molecules in the volume of a cell.)</p></li>
<li><p>Much of this acute sensitivity can be traced to <strong>D</strong>. (Much of this acute sensitivity can be traced to the collective behavior of teams of chemoreceptors on the cell surface.)</p></li>
</ul>

<p>This paragraph doesn&rsquo;t dumb the science down, it presents information in a way that&rsquo;s easy to assimilate. It opens with an interesting fact, it minimizes the use of technical terms, and it links new ideas with previous ones. Let&rsquo;s explore each of these strategies in turn.</p>

<h2>Open with interesting</h2>

<p>What does the chemotaxis network of bacteria do? It detects changes in concentration. Why is that interesting? Because it can detect very small changes. How small? As small as a 3-molecule change! OK, that&rsquo;s interesting. How about this?:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><u>Heparan sulfate (HS)</u> is a type of <u>linear oligosaccharide</u> in the <u>glycosaminoglycan (GAG)</u> family. HS consists of repeating <u>disaccharide units</u>, with <u>acetate groups</u> and <u>sulfate groups</u> modified at different regions along the sequence. HS chains are attached to <u>proteoglycan core proteins</u>, and bind to a variety of protein ligands, which as a whole, mediate <u>tissue-specific physiological functions</u>, including embryogenesis, angiogenesis, tumor metastasis, neuro-degeneration and host-pathogen recognition.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The interesting part of this paragraph is that heparan sulfate is a critical component in many cellular functions. But teachable newbies need to jump over 8 technical terms (underlined) to assimilate this insight. Exhaustive definitions never made anyone walk down to the conference room. Only interesting facts have the potential to do that.</p>

<p>This is my attempt at a rewrite:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Heparan sulfate proteoglycans are present in almost every cell type, they play crucial roles in a diverse array of cellular processes, from embryo formation to immune cell activation. The most important feature of these molecules is their GAG sequence, the string of repeating pairs of sugar molecules that define them.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Minimize technical terms</h2>

<p>My abstract makeover still has technical terms (HS proteoglycans, GAG sequence), but you no longer have to be familiar with them to follow the story. I can get away with not defining what <em>proteoglycan</em> means or what <em>GAG</em> stands for because driven experts don&rsquo;t need to be reminded, and teachable newbies can mentally replace them with &ldquo;this thing&rdquo; without losing any crucial information.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I replaced <em>disaccharides</em> with the more intuitive <em>pairs of sugar molecules</em> because I wanted to emphasize the importance of the GAG sequence. These compromises depend heavily on the audience, especifically on <a href="http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/04/21/speak-to-the-newbies-when-you-present-sheldon-cooper-vs-brian-greene/">what the least knowledgeable attendees are familiar with</a>.</p>

<p>This is a counter-example from a jargon-happy abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Computer-assisted motion analysis coupled to flash photolysis of caged chemoeffectors provides a means for time-resolved analysis of bacterial chemotaxis.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Technical terms are useful because they provide mental shorcuts but they&rsquo;re not free, they interrupt the reading flow of non-experts. If you must use them, do so sparingly, and only after you come up with a real-word alternative. Once you come up with multiple options for each technical term, you are in a better position to choose between being precise and being clear. Here are a few alternatives that mix precise technical terms and clear approximations:</p>

<ul>
<li><u>Our method</u> (clarity) provides a way to analyze <u>bacterial chemotaxis</u> (precision) over time.</li>
<li>Analyzing the <u>motion</u> (clarity) of each bacterium using <u>caged chemoeffectors</u> (precision) makes it possible to track their <u>response to external stimuli</u> (clarity).</li>
<li><u>Flash photolysis</u> (precision) allows us to <u>record bacterial trajectories in high resolution</u> (clarity).</li>
</ul>

<h2>Link ideas together</h2>

<p>Progressions are more satisfying than lists. Here is an abstract that lists five different ideas:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The new high-throughput and low cost sequencing technologies offer a wealth of opportunities to the scientific community. For example, in 2011, on average, 1.37 fully sequenced genomes became available every day. On the other hand, enzymatic processes have been studied by biochemists for many decades. But surprisingly, the knowledge gap between biochemistry and genetics is much more than what people expected: at least 36% of enzymatic activities have no representative sequence in any organism.</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li>Sequencing offers opportunities to scientists.</li>
<li>In 2011, a lot of genomes were sequenced.</li>
<li>Biochemists have spent a long time studying enzymatic processes.</li>
<li>There is a knowledge gap between biochemistry and genetics.</li>
<li>A big percentage of enzymatic activities don&rsquo;t have representative sequences.</li>
</ol>

<p>The problem with this paragraph is that the ideas are not linked. Does sequencing genomes imply scientific opportunities? What&rsquo;s the connection between biochemists and genetics? What links enzymatic activities with representative sequences?</p>

<p>Compare that to the way ideas progress in part 2 of the chemotaxis abstract:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Instead of receptors switching individually between active and inactive configurations, teams of 6-18 receptors switch on and off, and bind or unbind ligand, collectively. […] The advantage for chemotaxis is gain—[where] small relative changes in chemical concentrations are transduced into large relative changes in signaling activity […]. However, something is troubling about this simple explanation: in addition to providing gain, the coupling of receptors into teams also increases noise, and the net result is a decrease in the signal-to-noise ratio of the network. Why then are chemoreceptors observed to form cooperative teams? We present a novel hypothesis that the run-and-tumble chemotactic strategy of bacteria leads to a “noise threshold”, below which noise does not significantly decrease chemotactic velocity, but above which noise dramatically decreases this velocity.</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li>Teams of receptors cause chemotaxis by switching on and off collectively.</li>
<li>Chemotaxis provides gain.</li>
<li>Besides gain, it also increases noise.</li>
<li>Increased noise decreases the signal-to-noise ratio.</li>
<li>Why would increasing the signal-to-noise ratio be useful?</li>
<li>We think it&rsquo;s because the run-and-tumble behavior creates a noise threshold.</li>
</ol>

<p>Each new idea uses the previous one as a stepping stone, building satisfying anticipation and leading up to the conclusion (also known as <em>telling a story</em>).</p>

<p><hr></p>

<p>These are just tips. The best advice I can give is to write the kind of abstracts you would like to read, prioritize the newbies over the experts and iterate. Obscure scientific writing is not fun to write or read. Better science writing starts with our abstract.</p>

<aside>PS: the chemotaxis abstract is awesomely titled &ldquo;Why are chemotaxis receptors clustered but other receptors aren’t?&rdquo; and it was written by Dr. Ned S. Wingreen for the Boston University Systems Biology Seminar Series.</aside>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Writing Every Day Will Change Your Life</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/03/10/writing-every-day-will-change-your-life</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2014-03-10T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2014/03/10/writing-every-day-will-change-your-life</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>I&rsquo;ve spent the last 30 days writing at least one hour every day. Want to do the same? Here&rsquo;s how.</p>

<p>First, <strong>make a public commitment</strong>. Decide when you&rsquo;re going to start writing and how many days you&rsquo;re going to do it (30 days is a good starting point). Ask your friends to hold you accountable, make a bet with your cousin that you will write every day, post a daily update on your Facebook wall. Do anything to avoid having to answer the most dangerous question of all: &ldquo;Should I write today?&rdquo; Pondering this for any amount of time will lead to a thousand perfectly reasonable excuses on why you should skip today. Only the fear of public humiliation will keep you honest.</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<h2>How am I going to find the time to write?</h2>

<p>Never. You will never <em>find</em> the time to write, your only option is to <strong>make time</strong>. You have spent your life filling every idle moment of your day with some kind of activity; you won&rsquo;t get that time back without a fight. Choose what you&rsquo;re willing to give up—email, Facebook, clubbing, Netflix, shopping, Xbox—and carve out the time. I decided to give up reading news and checking email first thing in the morning; it freed up an hour and a half that I now use to write. The urge to go back to my old routine was strong during the first week—then it went away.</p>

<h2>How should I get started?</h2>

<p>If you find yourself sitting in front of the blank page, waiting for inspiration, do yourself a favor and <strong>stop writing</strong>. You might think that writing requires creating beautifully crafted paragraphs that cascade down elegant story lines. That&rsquo;s a lie. What you perceive as writing is the end result of a multi-stage process that started out with a simple <strong>outline</strong>. Every skyscraper in the world began as a rough sketch. You can come up with an outline in your Starbucks napkin while you wait for the bus. You can scribble it in your notebook during a boring seminar. You can type it with one thumb as you groggily fall to sleep. Outlines are easy to create, they elicit no expectations of perfection, and they plant the seeds of better writing.</p>

<h2>How do I develop the outline into a draft?</h2>

<p>You need to <strong>thrash</strong> before you draft. Some of the ideas in your outline will resonate more than others. Get rid of the boring ones and pick the ones that spawn a bunch of supporting ideas and point to interesting directions. Combine loosely connected ideas into themes. Remove the cruft from your ideas, unpack vague notions and turn them into clear statements. Multiple rounds of thrashing strengthen the foundation that underlies your writing. Without a sound structure, you will waste most of your time rewriting.</p>

<p>Once you are comfortable with the structure of your outline, it&rsquo;s time to make a commitment. Musicians are not allowed to rewrite the score in the middle of a performance. Likewise, <strong>you are not allowed to change the outline in the middle of the draft</strong>. Give yourself a time limit (say, one hour) and use it to develop the outline from start to finish. Some parts will be harder to develop—they could have probably used more thrashing—, but it&rsquo;s too late to go back now. Give it your best shot, and work with what you&rsquo;ve got. A firm deadline will make your creativity soar in ways you didn&rsquo;t think were possible. It will help you acquire the habit of solving problems with limited resources, and it will teach you the importance of thrashing early.</p>

<p>This is a crucial lesson. Before I learned it, I would spend 12 hours writing and rewriting a few paragraphs and never finish anything. It takes a lot of discipline to resist the perfectionist urge. When you&rsquo;re in the middle of the draft, it&rsquo;s surprising how many times you will feel that you need to rewrite your entire structure from scratch. This is self-sabotage and should be ignored. Once you finish the first draft—if you still have time—, you can do another round of thrashing and drafting (when you will likely discover that things were not as bad as you previously thought).</p>

<h2>When do I start revising?</h2>

<p>Only after you have written the first draft. Revising a day later is ideal; if you don&rsquo;t have enough time, at least wait a few hours. Your brain needs time to switch off the creativity factory and turn on the analytical engines. Revising is not about criticizing, it&rsquo;s about noticing. If you can pinpoint <em>why</em> something doesn&rsquo;t work, fixing it is easy. Your enemy is not a lack of literary ability, it&rsquo;s blindness. Developing the habit of noticing the things that hide in plain sight is the quickest way to make your writing sparkle.</p>

<h2>The rules of daily writing</h2>

<ol>
<li>Make your goal public. Other people are better at holding you accountable than you are.</li>
<li>If you don&rsquo;t know what to write, stop writing. Outline instead.</li>
<li>Thrash before you draft. Ensure that every idea in the outline is clear.</li>
<li>Timebox the first draft.</li>
<li>No thrashing and no revising while you draft.</li>
<li>Wait one day. Then revise.</li>
<li>Ship. Gather feedback.</li>
<li>Repeat</li>
</ol>

<p>Most ambitious projects are not about making huge leaps of genius and ability, they require taking a lot of small consistent steps. 30-day challenges are a great way of embracing this habit. I guarantee you that after 30 days of writing, you will be a different person. At the very least, you will know that you have the discipline and the determination to achieve your long-term goals. You will see new challenges as opportunities to face your fears and grow. I can&rsquo;t think of a better way to live.</p>

<p>Go out and write.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tim Minchin and the Power of Language</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/10/03/tim-minchin-and-the-power-of-language</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-10-03T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/10/03/tim-minchin-and-the-power-of-language</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>Tim Minchin is an irreverent, smart, and mercilessly funny comedian and musician. He has been recently awarded with an Honorary Degree from the University of Western Australia. During the ceremony he gave an <a href="http://www.timminchin.com/2013/09/25/occasional-address/">occasional address</a>, as he calls it, sharing nine of his poignant life lessons.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="480" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/yoEezZD71sc" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

<!--excerpt-->

<p>This guy is one of my heroes.</p>

<p>Here is my favorite quote from the speech:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Most of society’s arguments are kept alive by a failure to acknowledge nuance. We tend to generate false dichotomies, then try to argue one point using two entirely different sets of assumptions, like two tennis players trying to win a match by hitting beautifully executed shots from either end of separate tennis courts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now, that&rsquo;s an elegant piece of writing; or rather, a sequence of words, carefully selected for their ability to shape a clear thought inside the mind of the reader. Where is this vivid mental picture coming from? I can think of five components: the choice of words, the order in which they are arranged, the connections that they form with their neighbors, the ideas that these word connections elicit, and the order in which they appear.</p>

<h2>The right word at the right time</h2>

<p>Compare Tim&rsquo;s version</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Most of society’s arguments are kept alive by a failure to acknowledge nuance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>with this one</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The majority of arguments that take place in society happen because people don&rsquo;t bother with the details.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Why is Tim&rsquo;s version more elegant? I think it has to do with the mental pictures that our brain associates with each word. &ldquo;Keeping something alive&rdquo; offers more powerful imagery than &ldquo;taking place&rdquo;. Think about it. You can imagine administering CPR to someone, or trying to rekindle a burned out fire, but does &ldquo;take place&rdquo; or &ldquo;happen&rdquo; conjure anything? Not in my brain.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Not bothering with something&rdquo; is less dramatic than &ldquo;a failure to acknowledge something&rdquo;.</p>

<p>And then, there&rsquo;s &ldquo;nuance&rdquo;. I love that kind of words; rarely used but flawlessly fitting specific situations. &ldquo;Nuance&rdquo; describes a subtle shade of meaning; &ldquo;details&rdquo; as well, but it also has many other connotations that make it seem less focused: a detail can be an individual part of something, a particular of a story, a minor item, a thorough treatment.</p>

<h2>From abstract to visual</h2>

<blockquote>
<p>We tend to generate false dichotomies, then try to argue one point using two entirely different sets of assumptions, …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We are reading the sentence and we reach &ldquo;generate false dichotomies&rdquo;. Then, our working memory plants a flag—ok, that&rsquo;s one concept. Later, we get to &ldquo;argue… using two entirely different sets of assumptions&quot;—ok, another concept. Now we can look back to see the connection between &quot;dichotomy&rdquo; and &ldquo;arguing&rdquo; (a dichotomy is a division into two parts, we separate our assumptions into two camps and use them to argue the same point). The two ideas are connected, but the connection remains abstract until a metaphor comes along to accrue it into a shining visual:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>… like two tennis players trying to win a match by hitting beautifully executed shots from either end of separate tennis courts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is the power of language.</p>

<p>A few subtleties hold the visual together. Consider this more off-target version:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>… like tennis players hitting beautiful shots from their own court.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We could infer that there are &ldquo;two&rdquo; tennis players, that each is &ldquo;trying to win a match&rdquo;, that they are &ldquo;executing&rdquo; shots, that each is located at the &ldquo;end&rdquo; of a tennis court, and that the courts are &ldquo;separated&rdquo;, but noticing those things out requires too much mental work, and if they are not pointed out the visual crumbles.</p>

<p>This type of sentence dissection is not just being punctilious, it helps explain why some squiggles on the page manage to cajole our brain into comprehension better than other squiggles. And that&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;re after, right? Comprehension.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Simple Fix to Improve Sentences</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/30/a-simple-fix-to-improve-sentences</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-09-30T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/30/a-simple-fix-to-improve-sentences</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>One of the reasons why I maintain a blog is to become a better writer. I was doing a little text mining on my previous posts and I realized that I tend to start sentences with <em>There is</em> and <em>There are</em> when it is not really necessary. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>There is a lot of wizardry that surrounds the getline command.</li>
<li>There is a megaton of material we didn&rsquo;t cover, but here is a great link.</li>
</ul>

<p>This type of sentences are almost always improved by removing the <em>there is/are</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li>A lot of wizardry surrounds the getline command.</li>
<li>We didn&rsquo;t cover a megaton of material, but here is a great link.</li>
</ul>

<p>Matt Might has a nice <a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/shell-scripts-for-passive-voice-weasel-words-duplicates/">post</a> with advice on avoiding weasel words and lexical illusions.</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<p><hr></p>

<p>Tips that improve grammar are great, but I&rsquo;m still trying to figure out what I need to incorporate to my writing arsenal to <a href="http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/10/tearing-down-powerful-sentences/">craft sentences like Simon Winchester</a>. I keep coming back to this one, where he describes an ocean liner:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>She was fastened securely to the Pier Head, just beside the old Princes Dock, a dozen hemp ropes as thick as a man’s arm keeping her quite still, aloof to the weather. But from the bustle of last-minute activity around her and the smoke being torn urgently from her single yellow funnel, it was clear she was already straining at the leash: with her twenty-five thousand tons of staunchly riveted Clydeside steel, the Empress was readying herself to sail three thousand miles westward, across the Atlantic Ocean, and I had a ticket to board her.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The imagery, the choice of words, the pace, the conclusion; it&rsquo;s just brilliant.</p>

<p>I guess I&rsquo;ll just keep writing.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tearing Down Powerful Sentences</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/10/tearing-down-powerful-sentences</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-09-10T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/10/tearing-down-powerful-sentences</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>Crafting a sentence is just like solving a puzzle. Except that puzzles are solved by arranging every piece in the box until they form the picture that appears on the cover, and sentences are solved by fumbling with the limited set of words in your repertoire until the shifting idea in your head stops moving.</p>

<p>When I read great sentences, I am always surprised at how graceful they seem and I imagine the hours the author spent crafting them to sound just right. So I decided to start with a sentence I liked and go backwards. Consider this one, written by Simon Winchester in his book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Atlantic-Battles-Discoveries-Titanic-Million/dp/0061702625/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1378866077&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=simon+winchester+atlantic">Atlantic</a>. It talks about the maritime paintings of a Dutch master:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Even now, nearly five centuries on, these are paintings that grab the attention: invariably there is the hungry sea, its waves translucent green and white-capped, the troughs between them deep and dangerous and all providing a savage contrast to the distant comforts of cow-grazed meadows and church steeples.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now read a variation I won&rsquo;t publicly confess to having written:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Even though these paintings are almost five centuries old, they are still striking. The sea is usually stormy and full of tall green waves. It seems very different from the calm meadow and the village that are usually in the background.</p>
</blockquote>

<!--excerpt-->

<p>The first sentence resonates with my monkey brain; the second one is entirely unremarkable. When I first read Simon&rsquo;s sentence I didn&rsquo;t know why I liked it so much, so I decided to geek it out until I understood what made it so appealing. I&rsquo;m still not sure I uncovered all its secrets, but here&rsquo;s what I have so far:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>nearly</em> is classier than <em>almost</em></li>
<li><em>five centuries on</em> is more elegant than, say, <em>five centuries ago</em></li>
<li>The <em>now</em> plays well with the <em>five centuries on</em>. I like that the scene is set on <em>now</em>, then there is a reference to the past, and then we keep going. It&rsquo;s more satisfying than saying <em>Even though these paintings are almost five centuries old</em></li>
<li><em>grab the attention</em> is a more powerful visual than <em>are striking</em>.</li>
<li><em>grab</em> is a more powerful verb than <em>are</em>. I also like <em>the attention</em> more than <em>one&rsquo;s attention</em></li>
<li>the colon after <em>grab the attention</em> introduces the explanation for why they are striking. That connection would be lost by using a period.</li>
<li><em>hungry</em> is not an adjective typically used to describe the sea, it makes the sentence more vivid.</li>
<li>using a comma and describing the waves with <em>its</em> makes room for a richer description than simply appending adjectives (<em>tall green</em>)</li>
<li>The mental image I get from waves with white caps, and menacing troughs is of sharp teeth</li>
<li>there is a nice simmetry between <em>its waves translucent</em> and <em>the troughs between them</em> (<em>them</em> refers to the waves). <em>troughs</em> is precisely the right word to describe the negative space between two waves. They also each have five syllables, which helps.</li>
<li>there is a nice alliteration with <em>and</em>: <em>translucent and green</em>, <em>deep and dangerous and all providing</em></li>
<li><em>savage contrast</em>: another unlikely adjective-noun combination. It perfectly describes the feeling of comparing a dangerous sea with a quiet meadow.</li>
<li><em>distant comforts</em> is a better mental image than <em>in the background</em></li>
<li>I like the three adjective-nouns in a row: <em>savage contrast</em>, <em>distant comforts</em>, <em>cow-grazed meadows</em></li>
<li>the <em>all providing</em> rounds up the description better than <em>it seems</em>.</li>
<li>describing a meadow as <em>cow-grazed</em> is brilliant, and more vivid than a <em>calm meadow</em></li>
<li>a <em>church steeple</em> gives a crisper mental image than a <em>village</em></li>
</ul>

<p>A lot of pieces make up that puzzle. There are also no huge brilliant pieces; it is the combination of many good word choices and efficient structure that compounds the appeal of the sentence. I feel like knowing what the pieces are improves the chances of being able to use them to build my own sentences.</p>

<p>Here is another pearl by Simon, talking about an ocean liner. Feel free to tear it down:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>But from the bustle of last-minute activity around her and the smoke being torn urgently from her single yellow funel, it was clear she was already straining at the leash: with her twenty-five thousand tons of staunchly riveted Clydeside steel, the Empress was readying herself to sail three thousand miles westward, across the Atlantic Ocean, and I had a ticket to board her.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And these are just two sentences, imagine a whole book of them! I thoroughly <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Atlantic-Battles-Discoveries-Titanic-Million/dp/0061702625/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1378866077&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=simon+winchester+atlantic">recommend it</a>.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Writing Advice for Scientists</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/08/writing-advice-for-scientists</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/08/writing-advice-for-scientists</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>My appreciation for anyone who has ever written a research paper has skyrocketed during the past few weeks. I had to begin writing my own article to realize how mind-numbingly hard it is. Sometimes I feel like words refuse to leave my brain unless I force them with a corkscrew. Other times I stumble over booby-trapped paragraphs that kill whatever train of thought I had going.</p>

<p>Whenever I manage to write something coherent is because I take it one paragraph at a time, and when that doesn&rsquo;t work, one sentence at a time. In his <a href="http://www.americanscientist.org/issues/id.877,y.0,no.,content.true,page.1,css.print/issue.aspx">article on scientific writing</a>, George Gopen and Judith Swan share some of the most eye-opening insights I have ever read for crafting understandable sentences. I have spent a couple of hours poring over it and distilled it into two main guidelines:</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<h2>1. Use strong verbs, and place them close to their subjects</h2>

<p>This is a sentence from one of the articles I cite in my paper:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>While current infectious disease diagnostics rely on pathogen-based detection, the development of reproducible means for extracting RNA from whole blood coupled with advanced statistical methods for analysis of complex data sets now <u>allows</u> the possibility of classifying infections based on host gene expression profiling that reveals pathogen-specific signatures of disease.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sentences like this one show up everywhere. It&rsquo;s not obvious that <em>allows</em> is the crucial verb that comes after the comma because it is not a noticeable verb and also because it comes 23 words later, all jumbled up with statistical methods. Here&rsquo;s my attempt at improving it:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Current infectious disease diagnostics rely on pathogen-based detection, <strong>but an alternative method has recently become possible</strong>. <strong>Thanks</strong> to the development of reproducible means for extracting RNA from whole blood <strong>and the application</strong> of statistical methods to analyze complex data sets, infections can now be classified using pathogen-specific signatures of disease <strong>extracted from host gene expression profiles</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I split the first sentence into two to make the connection between the &ldquo;While&hellip;&rdquo; and the &ldquo;now allows&hellip;&rdquo; more explicit. I also added &ldquo;extracted&rdquo; to highlight the contrast between &ldquo;pathogen-based&rdquo; and &ldquo;host gene expression profiles&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>2. Begin sentences by introducing familiar topics and end them with emphasis-worthy information</h2>

<p>The reworked sentence above starts by talking about a <em>familiar</em> topic (the current diagnostics) and ends on emphasis-worthy information (there is an alternative method). The next sentence describes the previous developments that led to the new method and ends on the new method&rsquo;s key idea (using host gene expression profiles). An additional sentence could begin by describing how signatures of disease can be extracted from host gene expression profiles and end on why this is important (emphasis-worthy).</p>

<p>Going through the examples in the <a href="http://www.americanscientist.org/issues/id.877,y.0,no.,content.true,page.1,css.print/issue.aspx">article</a> helped me lay out my ideas a sentence at a time. I have found that arranging sentences into familiar topics and emphasis-worthy information helps me isolate ideas much more effectively and I no longer have to fret over fixing messy paragraphs.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I&rsquo;m still not done writing, argh. Back to work!</p>

<p>See you tomorrow.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I'm Starting a 30 Day Challenge to Get Back to Blogging</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/07/im-starting-a-30-day-challenge-to-get-back-to-blogging</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-09-07T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/07/im-starting-a-30-day-challenge-to-get-back-to-blogging</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>I randomly found <a href="http://jamimmunology.blogspot.com/2012/11/deletor-T-cells-singh-immunology-journal-club.html">this</a> blog post about T cells. It&rsquo;s written by Jamie Heather, an immunology PhD student in London, who posts his science thoughts online. He posts a few times a month, but he has kept it up for a few years. I only had to read a couple of his <a href="http://jamimmunology.blogspot.com/2013/05/up-goer-five-phd-description.html">older</a> <a href="http://jamimmunology.blogspot.com/2013/08/Decombinator-TCR-repertoire-analysis.html">posts</a> to realize that <em>this is a guy I could grab a beer with</em>.</p>

<p>Then I realized that the only content in my blog was four badly formatted posts with broken links, and that I hadn&rsquo;t posted anything new in two months. If browsing a few posts from a total stranger living in London made me think he was a cool guy, why am I not making it easy for other people to reach the same conclusion about me?</p>

<p>So I&rsquo;m starting a <strong>30-day challenge</strong>:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Every day, for the next 30 days, I will write something on my blog. It doesn&rsquo;t have to be earth-shatteringly interesting, funny or clever, just whatever I&rsquo;m thinking about that day. One paragraph is the minimum, two if I&rsquo;m feeling inspired.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To find time to write I&rsquo;ve also decided to quit my morning news-reading routine, which usually lasts an hour. I&rsquo;ve deleted all the newsy links on my toolbar to make it harder to fall into temptation. I&rsquo;ve also set up filters on Gmail to automatically remove the newsletters I&rsquo;m subscribed to from my inbox, and to tag them with a special label so I can check them after I&rsquo;m done working for the day.</p>

<p>With a bit of luck, 30 days will be enough to develop the writing habit, and I&rsquo;ll be ready to blog about my stay in French Guiana doing viral metagenomics. I should write a post about that soon.</p>

<p>Until then, wish me luck.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>