<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
   
    <title>reasoniamhere.com - Tag: productivity</title>
   
   <link>http://reasoniamhere.com</link>
   <description>I am a Spanish-born bioinformatics PhD student living in Boston</description>
   <language>en-us</language>
   <managingEditor>Nacho Caballero</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

    
      <item>
        <title>How to Stop Sabotaging Your Work</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/22/how-to-stop-sabotaging-your-work</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-09-22T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/22/how-to-stop-sabotaging-your-work</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>I keep forgetting how to defend myself against the feeling of <strong>being stuck</strong>—writers call it writer&rsquo;s block, painters call it feeling uninspired, runners don&rsquo;t have a name for it, they just suck it up and keep running—, so this post is a reminder on the two techniques that help me neutralize the resistance to get back to work.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/NhThbkn4hN5h_kj53hvrsVapMzrdqXK2zAxFLhirMnU=w561-h824-no" alt="basket"></p>

<!--excerpt-->

<h2>Give it your worst shot</h2>

<p>Perfectionists never get started. Instead of demanding yourself to instantly shape a flawless flow of ideas into a perfectly crafted paragraph, try giving it your worst shot. Lowering the bar from <em>perfection</em> to <em>drivel</em> short-circuits your brain into compliance.</p>

<p>Once you lay out the first imperfect ideas, you will find out that 1) they were not really drivel, and 2) they can be easily improved.</p>

<p>Trying to jump straight to the top is fruitless; mountains are climbed in incremental steps.</p>

<h2>Verbalize the roadblocks</h2>

<p>Other dangers await once you get started. They wield influence over you because they lay below the waterline of consciousness. Naming them is the only way to avoid getting stuck. Maybe the last sentence you wrote reminded you that you never changed the analysis to fit that new piece of data, or that the piece of paper where you wrote down the rationale behind your experiment is buried under a pile of papers.</p>

<p>Those are different problems from <em>I don&rsquo;t know what to write</em>. Realize that the focus has shifted from writing to problem-solving; make a decision about how to deal with the problems (depending on how important they are, and how much time they will take); and go back to writing. If you try to plow through without explaining why you feel stuck, your brain will eventually convince you that working is way less important than checking your email.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Birthday Wish Technique: How to Skip the Temptation to Procrastinate</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/11/the-birthday-wish-technique-how-to-skip-the-temptation-to-procrastinate</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/11/the-birthday-wish-technique-how-to-skip-the-temptation-to-procrastinate</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p><img src="/assets/birthday_wish_list.jpg" alt="My Birthday Wish List"></p>

<p>I remember being six years old and crying in my bed one night. I was outraged about something, and wanted my parents to come check on me. Eventually my dad came and did something completely unexpected. He asked me what I wanted for my birthday.</p>

<p>I immediately stopped crying. My birthday wasn&rsquo;t due in months. Was this some kind of ruse? Confused, I asked him if he planned to buy whatever I asked for. &ldquo;We will see&rdquo;, he said. So I told him, &ldquo;I want a skateboard&rdquo;, and went to sleep.</p>

<p>My parents never bought me that skateboard, but I can still remember how fulfilling it felt to simply ask for it.</p>

<p>Twenty four years later, crying is no longer an issue, but whining about not wanting to write a research article sometimes gets the best of me and leaves me procrastinating for hours. I usually love my work, and I love writing, but <a href="http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/09/08/writing-advice-for-scientists/">writing research papers is hard</a>. So I recently decided to apply the birthday wish technique that I learned back in my youth.</p>

<h2>The Birthday Wish Technique</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Grab a blank piece of paper and title it: <strong>When I&rsquo;m done working, I&rsquo;m going to:</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Keep it beside you while you work. Proximity is crucial.</p></li>
<li><p>Whenever you think of something you would rather be doing instead of working, write it down.</p></li>
</ol>

<h2>Why It Works</h2>

<p>Writing about something you are planning to do feels, in a way, like you have already done it. Ask any travel guide fanatic. Sometimes thinking about doing something feels even <em>better</em> than actually doing it. Ask anyone that just ate at a McDonald&rsquo;s.</p>

<p>The majority of the things that you write in your list will instantly lose their appeal the moment you finish working—they were part of the reality distortion field built by your brain to sabotage your attempts at accomplishing difficult tasks.</p>

<p>Spending a few seconds writing down what you crave, and getting back to work, can mean the difference between spending hours browsing the newsfeeds and finishing that damn report in time for salsa class.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to stay productive while working from home</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/01/04/How-to-stay-productive-while-working-from-home</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2013-01-04T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2013/01/04/How-to-stay-productive-while-working-from-home</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>I have been working from home since 2008 and I love everything about it: the freedom to set my own work hours, the lack of interruptions, the life-transcending 20-minute <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_nap#Benefits">power naps</a> after lunch. Working without adult supervision is empowering, but it can also be stressful. I remember the anxiety I had at the beginning, when I didn&rsquo;t know if I was working enough or too much, and struggled through work marathons that left me feeling tired and unproductive. Everything changed when I started tracking my work hours on a <a href="https://github.com/nachocab/track_me_now/blob/master/TrackMeNow.xlsx?raw=true">spreadsheet</a>. Seeing how much I was slacking or working took away all the guiltiness and stress of my workday.</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<h2>Plan</h2>

<p>Every morning I open my <a href="https://github.com/nachocab/track_me_now/blob/master/TrackMeNow.xlsx?raw=true">time tracker</a> and decide how many hours I would like to work (usually 7 hours). Then I estimate how long my breaks will be throughout the day (I take about 2 hours of unadulterated breaks, including lunch and nap). For example, if I sat down to work at 10:10, I would be done by 19:10.</p>

<div class="screenshot width_75"><img src="/media/track_me_now/plan.png"></div>

<p>If I know I have to run an errand at 18:00, I can either update my work goal or cut back on breaks. I like to make this decision before I start working, while I am still objective. It also promotes the healthy habit of working sustainable hours, which is the only way to be productive in the long run.</p>

<h2>Work</h2>

<p>Once I am happy with my work and break goals for the day, I clock in by entering the current time using Excel&rsquo;s shortcut <code>Ctrl Shift ,</code> (if your version of Excel is not in English, you might have to look up the shortcut. I know that in Spanish it is <code>Ctrl Shift .</code>). I might work for 45 minutes and then decide it is time for a break, so I go back to the tracker and clock out. I don&rsquo;t have a hard limit for how long my breaks are. The only rule is that I have to clock in once the break is over, that way I don&rsquo;t have to rely on my warped perception of time.</p>

<p>Clocking in and out throughout the work day makes it easy to see how much I have been working and how long my breaks have been. As I update the spreadsheet, the estimated end time is updated automatically. Depending on how I am doing, I might also manually update my work/break goal.</p>

<div class="screenshot width_75"><img src="/media/track_me_now/work.png"></div>

<p>I have a couple tricks for the few times when I forget to clock in or out:</p>

<ul>
<li>look at my browser&rsquo;s history to see when I accessed my email (usually the first thing I do when I am on a break)</li>
<li>check at what time I ran my last command on the <a href="http://www.cyberciti.biz/tips/howto-linux-unix-bash-shell-setup-prompt.html">terminal</a>, or in the <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/8480225/355567">R console</a>.</li>
<li>guesstimate</li>
</ul>

<h2>Review</h2>

<p>At the end of the day I look at my actual work hours, I decide how realistic my work goal actually was, and plan accordingly for the next day. That way I can plan accordingly for next day&rsquo;s goal. To start a new day, I simply select the B column in the tracker and press <code>Delete</code> to reset everything.</p>

<p>It might take some time getting used to, especially during the first week, or after a long vacation, but I hope it helps you gain a clearer picture of your work habits and makes you more productive.</p>

<p>Tell me if you found TrackMeNow useful. Comment below or star the <a href="https://github.com/nachocab/track_me_now">github page</a>.</p>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bioinformaticians need lab notebooks too</title>
        <link>http://reasoniamhere.com/2012/12/27/Bioinformaticians-need-lab-notebooks-too</link>
        <author>Nacho Caballero</author>
        <pubDate>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</pubDate>
        <guid>http://reasoniamhere.com/2012/12/27/Bioinformaticians-need-lab-notebooks-too</guid>
        <description><![CDATA[
           <p>Biologists preach to their undergrads: &ldquo;Write down everything you do in your lab notebook or in six months you will not remember why you did it&rdquo;. Quite true. I have tried to embrace this philosophy several times with pitiful results—probably because every time my subconscious convinced me that it wasn&rsquo;t worth the pain of implementing it; my code is in some file in my computer, so why bother?—Luckily, one day I discovered <a href="http://yihui.name/knitr/">knitr</a> and became a lab notebook fanatic.</p>

<!--excerpt-->

<p>Read Jeromy Anglim&rsquo;s <a href="http://jeromyanglim.blogspot.com.es/2012/05/getting-started-with-r-markdown-knitr.html">great tutorial</a> to get started with knitr and Markdown, or watch Yihui Xie&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.screenr.com/qcv8">video tutorial</a>. Now that knitr has taken center stage in my research, instead of hacking away at a problem, I create a knitr report and I intersperse my thought process with the code that I am writing, along with whatever figures and results get generated. It allows me to investigate different aspects of a problem to see which direction is more promising without losing sight of the big picture. I can also go back months later to know why I did something, or what my figures looked like. <a href="http://htmlpreview.github.com/?https://github.com/nachocab/knitr_reports/blob/master/example_reports/sample_report.html">This</a> is what one of my reports looks like, and <a href="https://github.com/nachocab/knitr_reports/blob/master/example_reports/sample_report.Rmd">this</a> is the code that I used to generate it.</p>

<p>I know a lot of people love RStudio, but I prefer to code in the text editor I know and love, <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a>. I have shared the <a href="https://github.com/nachocab/knitr_reports">snippets and commands</a> I use to generate knitr reports, for those who are interested. It doesn&rsquo;t matter what tools you use, the point is to stop analyzing data in a having-a-bunch-of-scripts mindset and transition into a everything-is-explained-in-my-lab-notebook mindset.</p>

<h2>knitr is awesome at</h2>

<ul>
<li>Sharing your results with your colleagues and advisors, at any stage of the analysis, without having to copy and paste images into a Word document.</li>
<li>Modifying all your figures in a single step (for example, if you want to rename the axes of all your figures).</li>
<li>Keeping track of code written in different languages (knitr supports R, Ruby, Bash, Perl, Python, Awk, among others)</li>
<li>Documenting command line workflows (for example, what arguments you used to call TopHat, Samtools and HTSeq in your RNA-Seq pipeline).</li>
<li>Coming up with easily modifiable examples to grok difficult statistical or machine learning concepts.</li>
</ul>

<h2>knitr best practices</h2>

<ul>
<li>Give meaningful names to your chunks. This ensures that generated images also get meaningful names. Chunk names must be unique to each report.</li>
<li>Save functions in an regular R file and call them inside your knitr report. This allows you to reuse your code and produces cleaner reports.</li>
<li>Use <code>opts_chunk$set</code> to set global chunk options, use local chunk options when needed.</li>
<li>Each report should have all its generated images in its own folder.</li>
</ul>

<p>The list goes on. If you have comments about how knitr has helped you with your research, please share.</p>

<h2>Links to learn more</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/yihui/knitr-examples">Yihui&rsquo;s examples on Github</a></li>
<li><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/knitr">Questions about knitr in Stack Overflow</a></li>
<li>Neil Saunders&rsquo;s <a href="https://nsaunders.wordpress.com/2012/08/27/custom-css-for-html-generated-using-rstudio/">great tutorial</a> on using knitr with custom CSS in RStudio.</li>
</ul>

        ]]></description>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>